なんば　むった
(南波六太)＜宇宙飛行士候補生➡
We astronaut candidates, or ASCANs,
通称アスキャンとなった私達は
他の国の候補生達との➡
have arrived in Houston, USA, for joint basic training with other candidates from around the world.
合同基礎訓練が行われるアメリカ･
ヒューストンへとやってきた＞
＜ケンジ せりかさん 北村さん
にった
ジャクサ
新田 ＪＡＸＡのオカンこと➡
Kenji, Serika, Kitamura, Nitta...
The mother of JAXA, Komachi, and veteran astronaut Murasaki.
小町さんと
むらさき
先輩宇宙飛行士の紫さん｡➡
そして私…ア～ンド アポ＞
And there's me.
And Apo.
＜１０日後から始まる訓練を前に
いえ
みんなはまず 家探しだ＞
Before we begin training in ten days,
we must find a place to live.
What kind of training should we expect?
＜これから先 どんな訓練が
私達を待っているのだろう＞
《こいつがヒビトの兄貴か…➡
This is Hibito's older brother?
ふぬけた顔をしてる｡
当然 軍隊経験もなし》
He looks rather dim.
Naturally, he has no military experience.
《弟に後れをとっている上に
この締まりのないふぬけ顔…➡
He's a step behind his little brother,
and he looks like a fool.
救いようのない
ノロマだと すぐ分かる》
It's clear that he's a lost cause.
宇宙飛行士ってのは アレだ…➡
If you ask me,
舞台役者に似てんだよなぁ｡
the astronaut business is like a theatrical production.
(紫)室長という名の
プロデューサーがいて➡
You have your producer, Chief of the NASA Astronaut Office.
You have your sponsors and trainers who provide direction.
スポンサーと呼ばれる
演出家がいるんだよ｡
じゃあ 俺らは何だ？ムッちゃん｡
So what does that make us, Mu?
《その日のコーヒーは
やたらと甘かった…》
That day, my coffee
tasted especially sweet.
Space Brothers
I can no longer remember
what I tried to forget
When I peeked through the telescope
I realized that our world is tiny
It was a picture of infinity
It's not a one-time thing
We'll walk together
Once we've passed the clouds,
we will hold the world between our fingers
and keep what we lost in mind
#47 The First Promise
クゥ～ン…｡
キャン！クゥ～ン…｡
クゥ～…キャン！
《ブルーやパープルや
ピンクやイエロー｡➡
Blue, purple, pink, and yellow...
なんとも色彩豊かな
カラフルスポーツ飲料が並ぶ国➡
The sports drinks in this country come in many different colors.
ここ アメリカ》
This is America.
甘そうな上に…毒っぽい｡
They look simultaneously sweet and toxic.
《しかし この地で暮らす以上
避けては通れぬ道…》
But since I'll be living here, I'll have to try one eventually...
《ミドリ…買っとくか！》
Green...
Guess I'll buy one.
《で ケンジにはレッドを
買って帰るか…》
And I'll get a red one for Kenji.
《ケンジ…》
Kenji...
《ケンジめ～…》
Damn you, Kenji.
(ケンジ)なぁ ムッ君｡
Hey, Mu...
Hmm?
毎回 この２年間の訓練中にさ…｡
Every time they hold this two-year training program...
あ…やっぱいいや｡ごめん｡
No, never mind...
Sorry.
えっ!?何だよ！
Huh? What was that about?
ちょっと ちょっと！
そういうの１番気になるんだって｡
Come on... Now you've made me curious!
Well, it won't make any difference,
いや 言ったって
仕方のないことだし➡
今言うべきことじゃないと
思ってね｡ごめん ごめん｡
so I shouldn't say anything now.
Sorry about that.
《何それ!?余計気になる！》
What does that mean?
Now I really wanna know!
現在
《チクショ～ ケンジの野郎…➡
Stupid Kenji...
紫さんに
一体何を聞いたんだよ!?》
What did Murasaki ask him?
《でも…言うべきことじゃない
ってことは➡
I guess it's something I'm not supposed to know yet.
今きくべきことじゃないって
ことなんだろう》
《わかってる わかってる｡
そうまで言われて➡
But I understand.
I'm sensitive enough to know I shouldn't pursue the matter.
しつこく聞くほど
俺はヤボじゃねえよ｡ふっ…》
ワン ワン！
《ふっふっふ…
ケンジにはもう聞かねぇ》
I won't ask Kenji.
《紫さんに聞こう！》
I'll ask Murasaki!
Oh, it's cute!
(北村)おお～ かわいい！
家具もついてんだ！
And there's furniture!
(小町)ええやんか ここ！
(せりか)私も ここでいいかも！
This is a nice place.
I like it.
スーパーも近いし｡
And it's near the supermarket.
《しかも キッチンが広い！
いっぱい作れる！》
Plus,
it has a big kitchen!
I can cook so much!
１人暮らしだったら 十分よね｡
It's more than big enough for one.
問題は家賃だね…｡
The problem is the price.
お兄ちゃん いくらや ここ？
(不動産屋)ああ はい ええっと…｡
How much will it cost, big guy?
Oh, uh...
Give us a good deal!
ドーンとまけぇや！ドーンと｡
あの子ら ああ見えて➡
Those girls are astronauts.
宇宙飛行士やで｡
ホンマ 安うしたって！
They're big shots!
そ…そうですね｡
A-Ah...
自分とこのマンションに
宇宙飛行士が住んでるなんて➡
Your apartments' value will increase with an astronaut living there!
かく
それだけで格が上がるがな！
すごい…｡
Amazing...
頼れる…｡
She's so dependable.
Yeah, that was a good deal!
いや～ 安うなった 安うなった｡
You girls are lucky...
ラッキーやったなぁ｡
小町さんて
英語ペラッペラですよね｡
Your English is terrific, Komachi.
(小町)せやろ！
ネイティブみたい｡
I know.
You speak like a native.
昔 カリフォルニアに
住んどったからな｡➡
I used to live in California.
So I've got a Californian accent.
バリバリのカリフォルニアなまり
の英語やけどな！➡
Let me know if you need help.
なんか困ったことあったら
呼んでや！
私がすぐに行ったるからな！
まかしとき‼
I'll come flying over.
I've got your back!
ありがとうございます｡
Thank you very much.
《おお～ すげえ たくましい》
She's so manly.
Want some marshmallows?
(小町)マシュマロ食べるか？
４個ぐらい 取りぃ！
You can have four.
≪ハァ ハァ…≫
(紫の同僚)ウウ～…ニンジャー‼➡
Ninja!
おいコラ！ニンジャー‼
Hey, Ninja!
ハアッ!?
H-Huh?
You did it again!
てめぇ またやりやがったな～！
うわ～ バレた！
He caught me.
くそ…また油性かなぁ｡
Damn...
Permanent marker again?
《ニンジャって呼ばれてんだ
紫さん》
They call Murasaki "Ninja"?
ハァ…あっ ムッちゃ～ん！
Hey, Mu!
こんにちは｡
Hello.
《まあ…》
Well...
⦅ニンニン ニンニン…⦆
The name does fit.
《納得…》
くっそ～ 今月２回目だよ｡
何で俺ばっかり…｡
Damn... That's twice this month.
Why does he keep targeting me?
(紫)飛行機でケンジ君に
言ったことねぇ…➡
What did I tell Kenji during the flight?
う～んと…どの話だろ？
Uh, what did I tell him?
なんか 訓練中にナントカって…｡
It had something to do with training...
ああ アレか！
そう！それです 多分…｡
Oh, that!
Yes, that... I think.
ちょっと反省してたんだよな｡
今 言うことでもなかったからさ｡
I regret telling him that a bit...
Since it's still a little early to tell you.
けど ケンジ君が色々質問してくる
から つい話しちゃったわけよ｡
But Kenji kept asking questions,
so I answered them.
なるほど～｡で 何を？
So that's it...
What did you say?
毎回 アスキャンの２年間の
訓練中からさ…｡
Every time the ASCAN undergo the two-year training,
もちろん 訓練後もだけど…➡
and even after training is over,
必ずと言っていいほど
だつらくしゃ
数名の脱落者が出るんだ｡
a few always leave.
要は辞めちまうんだよ｡
宇宙へ行くのを諦めんの｡➡
Basically, they give up.
Abandon their dreams of going into space.
訓練してみて 初めて気付く人も
そりゃいるさ｡
Some people don't realize until they begin training
自分には
向いてないってことにね｡
that they aren't really up to snuff.
《な なんてこった！》
That's crazy!
《いや 自分が諦めなきゃ
いいだけの話じゃねえか｡➡
Doesn't matter. As long as I don't give up...
なにビビってんだ》
Why should I be concerned?
《でも…➡
But...
でももし…その
｢向いてない数名｣が俺だったら》
But what if
I'm one of those that doesn't make the cut?
《ここまで来て…最後の最後で
夢破れるなんて…➡
After making it all the way here, my dream would be shattered.
That would be like...
それじゃまるで…》
《ド ドーハの…》
The Agony of...
《やめろ～‼
その先は言うな～‼》
Stop! Not another word!
まっ 気にするこっちゃねえよ｡
ムッちゃん｡➡
Well, you shouldn't worry about it,
Mu.
本当にしんどいのは
その先だぜ｡➡
It only gets worse from here.
いずれ分かる｡
You'll understand eventually.
(紫)おい！➡
Huh?
Hey, look over there.
あそこ見てみろ｡
ジェーソン･バトラー室長だよ｡
It's Chief Jason Butler.
Oh, that's the chief?
へぇ～ あれが室長｡
宇宙飛行士ってのは アレだ…
舞台役者に似てんだよなぁ｡
If you ask me,
the astronaut business is like a theatrical production.
(紫)室長という名の
プロデューサーがいて➡
You have your producer, Chief of the NASA Astronaut Office.
スポンサーと呼ばれる
演出家がいるんだよ｡➡
You have your sponsors and trainers who provide direction.
じゃあ 俺らは何だ？ムッちゃん｡
So what does that make us, Mu?
Actors.
役者｡
正解｡➡
Correct.
俺達 役者の誰を
舞台に立たせるかは➡
The producer chooses the actors who will stand on the stage.
プロデューサーの好みの
キャスティングによるんだわ｡➡
ちなみに 俺もミヤッチも
もう何年も 自分のことを➡
I should mention
that Miya-chi and I have been calling ourselves astronauts for many years,
宇宙飛行士と
名乗ってきたけどね…➡
いま
未だに 舞台にすら立てない
役者なんだよ｡
but we've never gotten the chance to step on-stage.
いずれ分かる｡
You'll understand eventually.
じゃ 俺は訓練に戻るわ｡
Well, it's back to training for me.
See ya around, Mu.
またね ムッちゃん｡
あ…はい｡
Oh, right.
ううう…甘い‼
It's sweet!
Damn it... He got me again!
《チクショウ…またもや》
《その日のコーヒーは
やたらと甘かった》
That day, my coffee tasted especially sweet.
《だけど 私は なんとなく
その味を覚えておく事にした》
However...
I decided that I'd remember that taste.
しゃくや
(新田)ああ 借家に決めたよ｡➡
Yeah, I decided to rent a house.
エルディーケイ
ガレージ付きの３ＬＤＫ｡
It has three bedrooms and a garage.
１人で住むには かなり広いな｡
部屋も余る｡
It's a little big for one person to live in,
Plenty of extra rooms.
やちん
そりゃ家賃も高くなるよ｡
Naturally, the rent isn't cheap!
なんで広い家にしたかって…｡
Why did I choose a bigger house?
まあ 一か八かだけど
あいつをこっちへ｡
Well, I'm hoping he'll live with me.
わかってるよ！だけど
このままじゃダメだって➡
I know!
But you know we have to do something, Sis.
姉ちゃんも思ってんだろ？
俺だって もうヤケクソだ！
I'm out of ideas.
悪い また電話する｡
みんなを待たせてるんだ｡
Sorry, I'll call you later.
People are waiting.
Wow! Michiko!
(ｼﾞｪﾆﾌｧｰ)ワォ！ミチコォ！
Jennifer!
ジェニファー！
It's been forever!
あ～ん 久しぶり‼
苦しい苦しい！死ぬて‼➡
It hurts! It hurts! You're killing me!
久しぶりやな～｡➡
It's been ages...
That's crazy...
What's this, Jennifer? You've gotten rounder!
ｼﾞｪﾆﾌｧｰ また丸なったんちゃうんか｡
《なんてこった…｡
知り合いなの この２人!?
》
They know each other?
Oh, you can tell?
あらっ わかる？そうなのよ｡
That's right...
だって 今ってハンバーガーが
おいしい季節じゃない？入る入る｡
The hamburgers taste best at this time of year.
I keep gulping them down.
《年中うめ～よ
ハンバーガーなんて》
Hamburgers are good year-round.
悪い 待たせた｡
全然｡
Sorry for making you wait.
You didn't hold us up.
わぁ～ スゴイ！
Incredible.
ミッションコントロールセンター｡
初めてだよ｡
The Mission Control Center!
It's my first time here!
私も！
(ケンジ)ﾓﾆﾀｰに映ってんのって➡
Mine, too!
Jennifer, is that moon footage up there live?
今の月面だよね
ジェニファーさん｡
That's right.
そ～よ フレディとバディが今
作業中なのよ｡
Freddy and Buddy are working right now.
Amazing!
スゴイ！
(北村)生だ 生だ！
Live footage!
なあ ジェニファー
ヒビトの様子は見れね～の？
Hey, Jennifer...
Can we see Hibito?
ヒビトは今 就寝中よ｡
起きるのは４時間後｡➡
Hibito's sleeping right now.
He won't be up for four hours.
心配しなくても ヒビトは元気よ｡
あんな事故の後だってのに➡
Don't worry, he's just fine.
He's still recovering from the accident,
and he's already begging to be assigned to an EVA operation.
早く船外活動をやらせてくれって
アピールしまくりよ｡➡
だけど ヒビトとダミアンには➡
But the doctors haven't cleared Hibito and Damian yet.
まだ ドクターのＯＫが
出てないのよね｡➡
残念だけど
あの２人に関して言えば…➡
Unfortunately, it sounds as though
they won't be allowed to participate in any EVA operations on this mission.
今回のミッションでは
もう船外活動はないと思うわ｡
マ…マジかよ｡
S-Seriously?
大丈夫よ｡基地内じゃ
低重力下での実験として➡
Don't worry...
There are experiments inside the base with spirulina cultivation and protein crystallization.
スピルリナって
ばいよう
藻の培養実験とか➡
けっしょうか
かいせき
タンパク質の結晶化や解析とか➡
They'll have plenty to tackle, so they won't be bored.
他にも山ほどやる事あるんだから
たいくつ
全然 退屈しないわよ｡
《まあ 仕方ね～よな》
Well, that was to be expected...
Actually, I feel better now.
《いや むしろ
そっちの方が安心か》
セス
(バトラー)ＣＥＳ-５１のクルーが
月面に立って➡
Two months have passed since CES-51 arrived on the moon.
２ヵ月が過ぎようとしている｡➡
Every day, they extend the record for the longest stay on the moon.
彼らは今 １日１日と 月面での
たいざい
こうしん
長期滞在記録を更新中だ｡➡
先日 月にいるナンバ･ヒビト
くんしょう
じゅよ
飛行士に勲章を授与した｡➡
Last month, one of the lunar astronauts, Nanba Hibito, was awarded a medal.
こうせき
彼の功績の素晴らしい点は
２つある｡➡
He did two things that were commendable.
傷を負った仲間を助けたことと➡
He saved an injured comrade,
自らも生きて帰ったことだ｡➡
while he also returned alive.
ナサ
我々ＮＡＳＡの最大のテーマは
そこにある！➡
That is NASA's key theme!
The realization of sustainable life on the moon.
じつげん
けいぞく
月面生活の実現と継続｡
とうたつ
そして 人類の火星到達｡
And also,
for humans to reach Mars.
我々の夢は尽きないが
その夢のためにも➡
We will do everything possible for our dreams,
必ず生きて帰ってくるという事を
約束してほしい｡
but I want you to promise that you will return alive.
これが室長である私
ジェーソン･バトラーと➡
This is the first promise between your chief, Jason Butler,
and the thirty of you ASCANs here.
この中にいる３０名の
アスキャン達との 最初の約束だ！
Okay, then.
そいじゃまあ 室長の
カタイ話は このへんにして➡
Enough serious talk from the chief!
Let's party now!
パーティーを おっ始めよう！
えっ カタかった？
Huh? Was I too serious?
はじめまして｡
(候補生)ヨロシク！
Nice to meet you.
It's a pleasure.
I look forward to working together.
(候補生)こちらこそ｡
As do I.
《へえ～ この人達が
俺達の同期生》
These people are our fellow candidates.
ザック･マコンネルだ｡➡
I'm Zack McConnell.
I may not bring much to the table,
ふつつかもの
不束者の こんな俺だが➡
ヨロシクたのむぜ｡
but I'm glad to be here.
I'm Nanba Mutta.
ナンバ･ムッタです｡
《同期なの この人？》
Is he one of us?
自己紹介に行かね～の ビンス？
スポンサーなのに…｡
Aren't you going to introduce yourself, Vince?
You are a sponsor.
It's because I'm a sponsor.
(ビンス)スポンサーだからです｡➡
I'll introduce myself one time in front of everyone.
自己紹介なんて 全員の前で
一発で済ませますよ｡
だけど 彼らの名前はまだ…｡
But you don't know their names yet...
(ビンス)彼らの顔と名前なら
はあく
すでに把握できてます｡
I've already learned their faces and names.
Wow, that's amazing.
(北村)わぁ～ スゴイ！
なんでわかるの？➡
How did you know?
Try Nitta next, then.
じゃあ 次
新田君 見てもらって！
えっ 俺？しょ～がねぇな…｡
Huh? Me?
Okay, I guess...
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)ど～ぞ ど～ぞ｡
Come this way.
どうしたの？
What's going on?
This lady is amazing.
彼女 スゴイよ｡
占いやってたらしいんだけどさ｡
She can tell fortunes.
She instantly knew that Itou is an only child,
見ただけで 伊東さんが
ひとりっ子だってわかったし➡
北村さんが
５人姉弟だってことも➡
that Kitamura has four siblings,
and that I have a wife, child, and little sister.
僕に妻と子供
妹が１人いることも当てたんだよ｡
予知能力もあるんですって！
She can even see the future!
Really?
マジで!?
Does she have super powers?
《それもう 超能力者じゃん》
ンンー！あなたは➡
You have...
ご家庭をお持ちのお姉さんが
１人と あと…➡
an older sister with her own family...
As well as...
弟さんが１人
いるんじゃないかしら？
one little brother.
《弟いんの…？意外》
He has a little brother?
That's a surprise...
(新田)惜しいね 姉はいるよ｡➡
Close.
I do have an older sister.
You got that part right.
ピッタリ あんたの言う通りだ｡
だけど…弟はいね～な｡
But...
I don't have a little brother.
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)あら～ 外しちゃったか…｡
Oh, was I wrong?
It was still impressive.
それでも スゴイよ！
ねえ 俺も 見て見て！
Say, can you do me?
ウッホン！
初めまして 日本からやって来た
ナンバ･ムッタです｡
Nice to meet you.
I'm Nanba Mutta, from Japan.
アマンティ･パテルです｡
インドから来ました｡
I'm Amanti Patel, from India.
《美人～‼》
She's pretty...
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)あなたには 弟がいるわ｡
まさしく！正解です！
You have a little brother.
Absolutely! You're right!
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)だって 有名だもの｡
ナンバ･ヒビトさん｡
After all, Nanba Hibito is very famous.
じゃ…じゃあなんかこう…
他のこと見てもらえないかな？
Then...
Then could you try something else?
Like how my future will go?
てんぼう
今後の展望的な…｡
Sure...
そうね…ンー｡
Hmm?
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)そ そうね…なんか
すごく イイ感じよ｡
It will go very well...
え…ホント ホントに？
Huh? Really?
R-Really...
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)ホ…ホントホント｡
ねえ アマンティ 私 カレーは
ライスよりナン派だってこと➡
Say, Amanti,
could you tell that I prefer curry with naan over curry with rice?
あなたにバレてる？
いいえ 今知りました｡
No, I just learned that now.
Then sometime, I'll teach you to make naan.
じゃあ 今度
でんじゅ
手作りナンを伝授します｡
Really?! Awesome!
本当!?やった～！
《ちょっと待て…》
Hold on...
ふおん
《明らかに…不穏な
表情したよな アマンティ》
Amanti looked very disturbed for a moment there.
ふん…｡
The stones out in the fields
are worn down by their daily existence and disappear
That's their trial
When will we be able to resist fate?
Before you lose all hope
and say that we can't win against gravity
go without stopping
past the goal line
You have such strong convictions
Leave your footprints on this Earth
Maybe their tiny length will cause a miracle in the end
Give us a magnificent jump
Run now and do it
Jump past all you see overhead
This is your stride
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#48 Always Have a Pedometer in Your Heart
＜アマンティの占い 何!?＞
What did Amanti see in my future?
Something will happen to me very soon.
＜絶対 近いうちに何かあるんだ
俺の身に＞
You will follow my orders,
(ビンス)＜君達は 私のやり方に
従ってもらい➡
and complete this two-year training in a year and a half.
本来 ２年間かかる基礎訓練を➡
１年半以内に
終わらせてもらいます＞
＜おっ｡ちょっとでも早く日々人に
追いつけるなら ありがたいぜ＞
Oh, I'll take any chance I can to catch up to Hibito.
＜で 最初の訓練は 何なんだ？＞
So what's up first in our training?
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Always Have a Pedometer in Your Heart"
(ビンス)＜あとは ただ ひたすら
歩いてもらう｡➡
You will start by doing a lot of walking.
それだけだ＞
And nothing else.
ひびと
(南波日々人)パンパカパーン！
This Week's Space Photo
Japanese astronauts performing well
This week's space photo!
今週の宇宙写真で～す！
カッコイイ！
Cool stuff!